Register of the Poland. Ambasada (United States) Records, 1918-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ambasada (United States) Records,
1918-1956
45015
Poland. Ambasada (United States)
111 manuscript boxes. (46.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, correspondence, bulletins, communiques, memoranda, dispatches, and instructions, speeches and writings, and printed matter, relating to the establishment of the Republic of Poland; the Polish-Soviet War of 1920; Polish politics and foreign relations; national minorities in Poland; the territorial question of Danzig, Memel, the Polish Corridor, and Galicia; the Polish emigration abroad; Poland during World War II; and the Polish Government-in-Exile in London. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/36/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (139 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/36/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Access Points
Minorities--Poland.; Poles in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Galicia (Poland and Ukraine); Gdansk (Poland); Klaip'eda (Lithuania); Lithuania.; Poland.; Poland--Boundaries.; Poland--Foreign relations--1918-1945.; Poland--Foreign relations--United States.; Poland--History--Wars of 1918-1921.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland--Politics and government--1918-1945.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--Poland.
Introductory Note
The United States and Poland established formal diplomatic relations in January 1919, a month ahead of the other Allied powers. During the next eleven years Poland was represented in Washington by an envoy in the rank of minister and, since January 1930, by an ambassador. The following diplomats were the Second Polish Republic's chief representatives in the United States:
The archives of the Polish embassy in the United States fared better than those of other Polish diplomatic posts. Most of the embassy's files were tranferred to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives during the 1930's. There about 38 linear meters survived World War II. This collection is now held in the Contemporary Records Archives (Archiwum Akt Nowych) in Warsaw. The rest of the embassy's records, as well as those generated during the war, remained in Washington until July 1945. When the United States withdrew its recognition from the London-based Polish government in exile, the Second Republic's Ambassador to the United States, Jan Ciechanowski, decided to protect all of the archival collections held in Washington from falling into the hands of the Soviet-sponsored government in Warsaw by transferring them to the Hoover Institution. The Hoover collection of the Polish embassy in Washington, supplemented by some related later emigre files and printed matter, occupies 111 manuscript boxes or about 14 linear meters. Ambassador Jan Ciechanowski's personal collection is held in the Archives of the Polish Institute and the Sikorski Museum in London.
Maciej Siekierski
June 1998
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1939-1951 (Box No. 1.)
  Correspondence of Ambassador Jan Ciechanowski and his office, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches And Writings Of Jan Ciechanowski, 1933-1956 (Box No. 2.)
  Arranged chronologically for untitled items and alphabetically by title for titled items
- Despatches And Instructions, 1919-1944 (Box No. 2-4.)
  Despatches sent by the Polish Ambassador and his office to the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and instructions sent by the Ministry to the Ambassador and his office, arranged as listed
- Reports, 1920-1947 (Box No. 4-34.)
  Reports sent by the Embassy to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, as well as reports received by the Embassy from the Ministry, other Polish consular and diplomatic posts, Polish government offices, and various other governmental bodies. Arranged in two subseries, one arranged alphabetically by office and the other arranged alphabetically by subject
- Bulletins, 1919-1953 (Box No. 34-39.)
  Official bulletins of the Government of the Republic of Poland and other governmental or intergovernmental bodies, arranged alphabetically by name of government or of intergovernmental body
- Communiques, 1920 (Box No. 39.)
  Military communiques from the Polish High Command, forwarded to the Polish Embassy by the Polish Military and Naval Attache Plenipotentiary, arranged chronologically
- Telegrams Sent And Received, 1939-1945 (Box No. 39-42.)
  Typed transcripts of telegrams sent to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and to other diplomatic offices, and of telegrams received from the Ministry and from other offices and deciphered by the Polish Embassy in Washington, arranged chronologically. Most telegrams received originate with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
- Circulars, 1920-1951 (Box No. 43-45.)
  Polish government circulars, arranged alphabetically by office of origin
- Memoranda, 1918-1947 (Box No. 45-46.)
  Memoranda written by Ambassador Jan Ciechanowski and others, arranged alphabetically by last name of author or, if author is unknown, by subject
- Paraphrases Of And Notes For Conversations, 1931-1944 (Box No. 46.)
  Paraphrases of diplomatic talks and notes in preparation for such talks, arranged chronologically
- Printed Matter, 1936-1956 (Box No. 46-47.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of author or, if author is unknown, by title
- Subject File, 1919-1952 (Box No. 47-110.)
  Letters, notes, drafts of letters, telegrams, reports, clippings, memoranda, printed matter, lists, statements, declarations, studies, despatches, carbon copies, photocopies, etc., arranged alphabetically
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1951
  - Byrnes, James F., July 5, 1945 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Celler, Emanuel, 1944 (Folder 2)
  - Cicognani, Amleto Giovanni, Archbishop, 1944 (Folder 3)
  - Cross, Samuel H., 1942 (Folder 4)
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1945 (Folder 5)
  - Dunn, James C., 1943 (Folder 6)
  - Gwiazdoski, Tadeusz, 1947-1949 (Folder 7)
  - Hull, Cordell, 1944-1945 (Folder 8)
  - Jachimowicz, Jan, 1950 (Folder 9)
  - Jedrzejewski, Stefan, 1951 (Folder 10)
  - Jelenski, Konstanty, 1948-1949 (Folder 11)
  - Kukiel, Marian, General, 1947-1949 (Folder 12)
  - Masaryk, Jan, 1942 (Folder 13)
  - Powell, E. H., 1942 (Folder 14)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1943 (Folder 15)
  - Stanczyk, Jan, 1941 (Folder 16)
  - Tarnowski, Adam, 1945-1947 (Folder 17)
  - Various Polish consular and diplomatic posts, 1941-1947 (Folder 18)
  - Diplomatic notes to and from various foreign diplomatic offices
    - 1939 (Folder 19)
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 20)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1933-1956
  - Untitled (Box 2.)
    - 1940-1956 (Folder 1)
    - 1945-1951 (Folder 2-3)
  - Titled
    - "German-Polish Relations," article reprinted from International Affairs, May-June 1933 (Folder 4)
    - Speech given in honor of Dorothy Thompson, May 6, 1941 (Folder 5)
    - Speech (untitled), 1941 or 1942 (Folder 6)
    - Speech given at the Cooperative Forum, September 23, 1942 (Folder 7)
    - Speech (untitled), 1942 (?) (Folder 8)
    - Speech (untitled), March 3, 1947 (?) (Folder 9)
    - Speech given at Americans of Polish Descent rally, Cleveland, Ohio, October 30, 1950 (Folder 10)
    - Statements, July 1945 (Folder 11)
- DESPATCHES AND INSTRUCTIONS, 1919-1944
  - General (Box 2.)
    - 1919-1921 (cablegrams) (Folder 12-15)
    - 1919-1921 (cablegrams) (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 3)
    - 1922 (Folder 4-7)
    - 1926 (December 25, 1925 -December 31, 1926) (Box 4., Folder 1)
    - 1927 (January 4 -December 31) (Folder 2)
    - 1928 (January 3 -November 26) (Folder 3)
    - 1929 (December 31, 1928 -December 27, 1929) (Folder 4)
  - Instructions from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs to the various diplomatic and consular posts
    - 1939
      - October 10 (Folder 5)
      - November 28 (Folder 6)
    - 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous despatches and instructions, 1942 (Folder 8)
- REPORTS, 1920-1947
  - Reports by office (Box 4.)
    - Commission of Financial Advisers, 1926
      - Accounting and fiscal control (Folder 9)
      - Bank of Poland - Revision of articles of association (Folder 10)
      - Banking fund, Proposed (Folder 11)
      - Budget law (Folder 12)
      - Customs administration (Folder 13)
      - Danzig - Customs administration (Folder 14)
      - Public debts policy (Folder 15)
      - Remarks on recommendations of Commission (Folder 16)
      - Revenue system, Polish (Box 5., Folder 1)
      - Salt industry (Folder 2)
      - Tobacco monopoly (Folder 3)
      - Zloty, Stabilization of (Folder 4)
    - General Staff - Department II (Sztab Glowny - Oddzial II). Analyses of German military budget for 1930/1931 (July 1930) and for 1931/1932 (June 1931) (Folder 5-6)
    - Inter-Allied Research Committee. Potulicki, M., Dr., "Some Aspects of the Organization of German Thinking," October 1944 (Folder 7)
    - Ministerial Committee of Enquiry into the Question of the Polish Prisoners of War from the 1939 Campaign, Missing in the USSR
      - "Facts and Documents Concerning Polish Prisoners of War Captured by the USSR during the 1939 Campaign," February 1946 (Folder 8)
      - "The Mass Murder of Polish Prisoners of War in Katyn," March 1946 (Box 6., Folder 1)
      - "Supplementary Report on Facts and Documents Concerning the Katyn Massacre," October 1947 (Folder 2)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych (Ministry of Internal Affairs). Wydzial Narodowosciowy (Nationalities Section). "Geneza i rozwoj ukrainskiego ruchu nacjionalistycznego /UWO i OUN" (Genesis and Development of the Ukrainian Nationalist Movement - UVO and OUN), 1933 (Folder 3)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych /MSZ (Ministry of Foreign Affairs)
      - General
        - 1919, from Department of Information - "Report on Ukrainian Cruelties Committed on the Polish Population of Eastern Galicia" (Folder 4)
        - 1919-1921 (Folder 5-7)
        - 1919-1921, from Sekretarjat Spraw Politycznych (Secretariat of Political Affairs) (Folder 8-9)
        - 1920, from Ministry - by W. Lednicki (Folder 10)
        - 1920-1924, to and from Ministry and Washington, D.C. Embassy (Folder 11)
        - 1921, from Dyrekcja Spraw Politycznych (Directorate of Political Affairs) (Folder 12)
        - 1921, from Dyrekcja Spraw Politycznych. Wydzial Wschodni (Eastern Division). "Sprawa Galicji Wschodniej" (The Matter of Eastern Galicia) and "Ukraina" (Ukraine) (Folder 13)
        - 1927, to and from Ministry and various embassies (Box 7., Folder 1)
        - 1928, to and from Ministry and various embassies (Folder 2)
        - 1930, to and from Ministry, the Ministry of Industry and Commerce, and other embassies (Folder 3-4)
      - Copies, received or made at the Washington Embassy of reports on foreign affairs sent by various Polish embassies to the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs
        - Chronological file
          - 1921 (Folder 5)
          - 1929 (Folder 6)
          - 1931-1934 (Folder 7)
          - 1932-1933 (Folder 8-9)
          - 1933 (Folder 10)
          - 1934 (Folder 11)
          - 1934-1937 (Box 8., Folder 1)
          - 1935-1936 (Folder 2)
          - 1936 (Folder 3-4)
          - 1937 (Folder 5-6)
          - 1938 (Folder 7-8)
          - 1938-1939 (Folder 1-2)
          - 1939-1940 (Folder 3-6)
          - 1941 (Folder 7)
          - 1940-1941 (Box 10., Folder 1-4)
          - 1941-1942 (Folder 5-6)
          - 1941-1942 (Box 11., Folder 1-3)
          - 1942-1943 (Folder 4-7)
          - 1942-1943 (Box 12., Folder 1-2)
          - 1943-1944 (Folder 3-7)
          - 1944-1945 (Box 13., Folder 1-3)
          - 1946-1947 (Folder 4)
        - Alphabetical file
          - Ankara Embassy, 1944 (Folder 5)
          - Berlin Embassy
            - 1923-1924 (Folder 6)
            - 1925-1931 (Folder 7)
            - 1926 (Folder 8)
            - 1926-1927 (Folder 9)
            - 1927 (Folder 10)
            - 1927-1931 (Box 14., Folder 1)
            - 1928 (Folder 2)
            - 1932 (Folder 3)
          - London Embassy
            - 1923 (Folder 4-6)
            - 1924-1925 (Folder 7)
            - 1926 (Box 15., Folder 1-4)
            - 1927 (Folder 5-7)
            - 1927 (Box 16., Folder 1)
            - 1928 (Folder 2-3)
            - 1928-1929 (Folder 4)
            - 1929 (Folder 5-6)
            - 1930 (Folder 7-8)
            - 1931 (Box 17., Folder 1-2)
            - 1932 (Folder 3-4)
            - 1933 (Folder 5-7)
            - 1934 (Box 18., Folder 1-2)
            - 1935 (Folder 3-5)
          - Madrid Embassy, 1946-1947 (Folder 6)
          - Paris Embassy
            - 1923-1924 (Folder 7)
            - 1926 (Folder 8)
            - 1926-1927 (Box 19., Folder 1)
            - 1927 (Folder 2-5)
            - 1928 (Folder 6-7)
            - 1929-1930 (Box 20., Folder 1)
            - 1931 (Folder 2)
            - 1932-1933, 1937 (Folder 3)
          - Vatican Embassy
            - 1936, 1940-1941 (Folder 4)
            - 1940-1941 (Folder 5)
      - Drafts and copies of reports sent by the Washington Embassy to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
        - Political reports
          - 1919-1920 (Folder 6)
          - 1920 (Folder 7)
          - 1920-1921 (Box 21., Folder 1)
          - 1921 (Folder 2-3)
          - 1922
            - January (Folder 4)
            - February (Folder 5)
            - March (Folder 6)
            - April (Folder 7)
          - 1923 (Box 22., Folder 1-2)
          - 1924 (Folder 3-4)
          - 1925 (Folder 5)
          - 1926 (Folder 6-7)
          - 1926 (Box 23., Folder 1-3)
          - 1927 (Folder 4-6)
          - 1928
            - January-February (Folder 7)
            - March-April (Box 24., Folder 1)
            - May-June (Folder 2)
            - July (Folder 3)
            - October-December (Folder 4)
          - 1929 (Folder 5-6)
          - 1930 (Folder 7)
          - 1930 (Box 25., Folder 1-2)
          - 1931 (Folder 3-4)
          - 1932 (Folder 5)
          - 1933 (Folder 6-7)
          - 1934-1936 (Box 26., Folder 1)
          - 1936 (Folder 2-3)
          - 1941 (Folder 4)
          - 1942 (Folder 5)
          - 1943 (Folder 6)
          - 1944 (Folder 7)
          - 1944 (Box 27., Folder 1)
          - 1945 (Folder 2)
        - Press reports
          - 1934 (Folder 3)
          - 1935 (Folder 4)
          - 1938 (Folder 5)
          - 1939 (Folder 6)
          - 1941 (Folder 7)
          - 1942 (Box 28., Folder 1)
          - 1943 (Folder 2)
          - 1944 (Folder 3)
          - 1945 (Folder 4)
    - Polish Consulate, Montreal, 1937 (Folder 5)
    - Polish Consulate, New York, 1939 (Folder 6)
    - Polish Consulate, Pittsburgh. Reports, sent to the Washington Embassy, on Ukrainian affairs, 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Polish Consulate, Pittsburgh. Reports, sent to the Washington Embassy, on Ukrainian affairs, 1941 (Box 29., Folder 1)
    - Polish Government, London
      - "Report on Conditions in Poland," November 27, 1942 (Folder 2)
      - "The Scope and Activities of the National Socialist Party in the German Reich" (Folder 3-4)
    - Polish Government - Plenipotentiary in Poland. "Prisons and Concentration Camps," January, 1945 (Folder 5)
    - Polish Legation, Moscow. Reports and copies of reports by the Polish Legation in Moscow sent to the Polish Embassy in Washington, D.C. or to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Warsaw
      - 1929 (Folder 6)
      - 1929 (Box 30., Folder 1)
      - 1930 (Folder 2-3)
  - Reports by subject
    - Allies - Relations with Poland and the USSR. "Sprzymierzeni Polska i Rosja Sowiecka" (The Allies, Poland and Soviet Russia), 1941 (in Polish) (Folder 4)
    - Borders, Polish. Jedrzejewski, Klemens, "Odra-Nisa: Polski najlepsza granica" (The Oder-Neisse: Poland's Best Border) (Folder 5)
    - Carpatho-Rus' press in the U.S., 1943-1944 (Folder 6)
    - Catholic Church, 1944. Report by Oscar Halecki (Folder 7)
    - Deportations of Polish citizens to the USSR, 1940-1941 (Folder 8)
    - Economy, European (Folder 9)
    - Economy, Polish - Commerce with Germany (Folder 10)
    - Emigration and immigration
      - Austrian (Folder 11)
      - German (Folder 12)
      - Polish
        - General (Folder 13)
        - Aid for Poland, 1920 (Folder 14)
        - Campaign against foreigners, 1935 (Folder 15)
        - Committee for the Defense of Poland, 1920 (Folder 16)
        - Communist movement (Folder 17)
        - Elections, U.S., 1936, Role in (Folder 18)
        - Emigration laws (Folder 19)
        - Haller, General, Demobilized soldiers of, 1920 (Folder 20)
        - Press, Polish, abroad (Folder 21)
        - Socialist movement (Folder 22)
    - Germany (Box 31.)
      - Politics (Folder 1)
      - Relations with, 1942-1943 (Folder 2)
    - Latin America. Report by M. Kwapiszewski, July 21, 1943 (Folder 3)
    - Lithuanian affairs
      - General
        - 1920-1921 (Folder 4)
        - 1924 (Folder 5-6)
        - 1925 (Folder 7-9)
      - Reports by Klemens Jedrzejewski, 1942-1943 (Box 32., Folder 1-4)
    - Occupation of Poland
      - German
        - General (Folder 5)
        - 1940-1941 (Folder 6)
        - 1942 (Folder 7)
        - 1943 (Folder 8)
        - 1943-1944 (Box 33., Folder 1)
      - German and Soviet, 1939-1940 (Folder 2-3)
      - Soviet, 1943 (Folder 4)
    - Plebiscite in Soviet-occupied Poland. Jedrzejewski, K., "Plebiscyt" (The Plebiscite), February 21, 1944 (Folder 5)
    - Poland - General situation
      - 1943. Report by Klemens Jedrzejewski (Folder 6)
      - 1946. Reports by Adam K. Niebieszczanski, 1946 (Folder 7)
    - Press, Argentine (Folder 8)
    - Press, U.S.
      - On Poland (Folder 9)
      - 1942 (Folder 10-12)
    - Propaganda, Soviet (Box 34., Folder 1)
    - Ukrainian affairs, 1942 (Folder 2)
    - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR)
      - Corrective labor camps, 1941. Report sent by Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych (Ministry of Foreign Affairs) to the Washington, D.C. Embassy (Folder 3)
      - Economy, 1930-1931, 1940, 1944 (Folder 4)
      - Foreign relations
        - Poland
          - General, 1944-1945. Included are reports by Klemens Jedrzejewski (Folder 5)
          - "Polska i Rosja" (Poland and Russia) by Martin Seyda (Folder 6)
          - "Sprawa Polska..." (The Polish Issue...) by Klemens Jedrzejewski (Folder 7)
        - England and the U.S. (Folder 8)
      - Nationalities policy, 1943 (Folder 9)
    - War relief
      - Deportees, Polish, in the USSR (Folder 10)
      - Population in occupied Poland (Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous. Copies of reports on various subjects sent to Ambassador Ciechanowski, 1943 (Folder 12)
- BULLETINS, 1919-1953
  - Inter-Allied Research Committee, 1944 (Box 34., Folder 13)
  - Latvian Legation, Washington, D.C. Press Bureau. Latvian Information Bulletin, No. 46, May 1941 (Folder 14)
  - Poland, Republic
    - Department of Information. La decade polonaise, No. 10, Paris, April 10, 1940 (continued by Polish Press Bureau, London, as Polish News Bulletin) (Folder 15)
    - Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji (Ministry of Information and Documentation)
      - General, 1944 (Folder 16)
      - Bulletins and press reports
        - 1944 (Folder 17)
        - 1944-1945 (Box 35., Folder 1)
      - Polish News Bulletin, resume of Nos. 1-5, London, February 7, 1945 (Folder 2)
    - Ministerstwo Przemyslu i Handlu. Departament Handlowy (Ministry of Industry and Commerce. Commercial Department). "Biuletyn Informacyjny" (Information Bulletin), 1931-1932 (Folder 3-5)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych (Ministry of Internal Affairs)
      - "Przeglad Polskiej Prasy Podziemnej" (Review of the Polish Underground Press)
        - No. 3, 1943 (Folder 6)
        - Nos. 16 & 16a, 1944 (Folder 7)
      - "Sprawozdanie" (Report)
        - No. 6, November 22, 1943 (Folder 8)
        - No. 8, October 18, 1943 (Box 36., Folder 1)
        - No. 14, 1944 (Folder 2)
        - No. 17, December 12, 1944 (Folder 3)
      - "Sprawozdanie Krajowe," No. 1, April 30, 1943 (Folder 4)
      - "Sprawozdanie Sytuacyjne z Ziem Polskich," No. 9, May-June 1943 (Folder 5)
      - "Straty Kulturalne" (Cultural Losses), "Raport," No. 18, I-III, December 1944 (Folder 6)
      - "Sytuacja w Ruchu Komunistycznym za Czas od 18 Sierpnia do 10 Wrzesnia 1943 r." (The Situation in the Communist Movement During the Period From August 18 to September 10, 1943), "Sprawozdanie," No. 1A, January 25, 1944 (Folder 7)
    - Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych
      - General
        - "Komunikaty Wschodnio-Galicyjskie" (Eastern Galician Communiques), 1921-1922 (Folder 8)
        - "Ministry of Foreign Affairs Information Bulletin - Polska a Zagranica" (Poland and Foreign Countries)
          - February 1944 -January 1945 (Folder 9)
          - February 1944 -January 1945 (Box 37., Folder 1)
      - Departament Polityczny (Political Department). "Polska a Zagranica" (Poland and Foreign Countries)
        - 1923 (Folder 2)
        - 1927 (Folder 3)
      - Departament Polityczno-Ekonomiczny (Political Economic Department). "Polska a Zagranica" (Poland and Foreign Countries)
        - 1928 (Folder 4)
        - 1929 (Folder 5-6)
        - 1930 (Folder 7)
        - 1931 (Folder 8)
        - 1931 (Box 38., Folder 1)
        - 1932 (Folder 2-5)
      - Wydzial Wschodni. Referat Informacyjny (Eastern Department. Information Bureau). "Biuletyn Informacyjny o Rosji i Ukrainie Sowieckiej" (Information Bulletin on Soviet Russia and the Ukraine), November-December 1922 (Folder 6)
    - Polish Congress Delegation. Political Department. "Kronika Polskoukrainska" (Polish-Ukrainian Chronicle), 1919-1920 (Folder 7)
    - Polish Press Bureau, London. Polish News Bulletin, La decade polonaise, No. 12, ca. 1940 (Folder 8)
    - Polska Agencja Telegraficzna /PAT (Polish Telegraph Agency)
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 9)
      - 1949-1953 (Box 39., Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous bulletins of the Polish Government in London
      - "Biuletyn Informacyjny" (Information Bulletin), October 1945 -July 1946 (Folder 2)
      - "Informacje Ogolne" (General Information), 1946 (Folder 3-4)
      - "List Informacyjny" (Information Sheet), 1946-1948 (Folder 5)
      - "Wiadomosci Krajowe" (News from the Homeland), No. 25 (May) and No. 27 (June), 1948 (Folder 6)
  - United States of America. Department of State. Department of State Bulletin (excerpts), 1939-1945 (Folder 7)
- COMMUNIQUES, 1920
  - Pelnomocnik Wojskowy i Morski przy Poselstwie Polskiem w Waszyngtonie (Military and Naval Attache Plenipotentiary at the Polish Embassy in Washington). Communiques from the Polish High Command, 1920 (Box 39., Folder 8)
- TELEGRAMS, SENT TO AND RECEIVED FROM THE MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND OTHER POSTS, 1939-1945
  - 1939, Volume II (Box 39., Folder 9)
  - 1939, Volume II (Box 40., Folder 1)
  - 1940 (Folder 2-3)
  - 1941
    - January-April (Folder 4)
    - May-August (Folder 5)
    - September-December (Folder 6)
  - 1942
    - January-March (Folder 7)
    - March-April (Folder 8)
    - May-June (Box 41., Folder 1)
    - July-August (Folder 2)
    - September-October (Folder 3)
    - October-December (Folder 4)
  - 1943
    - January-March (Folder 5)
    - March-May (Folder 6)
    - June-September (Folder 7)
    - October-December (Box 42., Folder 1)
    - September 17, 1943 (from Minister of Foreign Affairs) (Folder 2)
  - 1944
    - January-March (Folder 3)
    - April-June (Folder 4)
    - July-September (Folder 5)
    - October-December (Folder 6)
  - 1945
    - January-March (Folder 7)
    - April-July 5 (Folder 8)
- CIRCULARS, 1920-1951
  - Poland, Republic (Box 43.)